It's my favorite TV family,
the Griffins.
(all gasping)
Victory is mine!
(exclaiming)
Go on, get out!
(screaming)
Housekeeping.
Bing bong!
Mommy! Mama!
You're a phony.
Meg?
(yelling)
(gasps)
(retching)
What do you want,
a Cleveland steamer?
All right.
Bringing the
good news today?
It's gonna rain!
(laughs) Yes!
No...
(laughing)
(giggling)
Ah, that's right!
I think at one point, I thought
we would get to 200 episodes,
and then when we got canceled,
I thought, "No, we won't get
to 200 episodes."
And then, when we came back,
I thought, "Yeah, maybe
we'll get to 200 episodes."
And now, it's like,
"Oh, crap, 200 episodes."
I'm so proud of you.
Way to go, Dad.
Yeah, you're
a smart fella, Dad.
And you're
a fart smeller, Meg.
(farts)
(screams)
(laughs)
Wait. We've been on for 200
episodes?
Wow. I'm actually almost...
What I've done is
I wanted my weight
to equal how many
episodes we have.
So I'm almost, I'm just about
at 200 pounds.
And I plan to continue
to rise with the episodes.
So, if the show goes 500
episodes, I will not be able
to leave my house.
(beeping)
I've always found it really
funny
and I was excited when
so many other people did
'cause it meant that
all have in common.
We all find this funny.
This is a show
that has never tried
to be anything more
than something that
makes you laugh as often
and as loudly as possible
within the course
of a half hour.
(screaming)
(bleeping)
Damn it!
Oh, my God.
Peter, are you okay?
No! I am not okay.
Nothing about
this is okay.
Inherently, like, in the show's
DNA,
has the ability to go a lot of
different directions.
We could tell conventional
family stories that are
very character driven.
I say it's four o'clock,
away with you.
Stewie!
Change it back!
No, forget it.
Jolly Farm Revue is on.
It's the latest
indoctrinating pabulum
for children with
not enough to do.
Hey! Shut up.
And also, you could tell
buddy comedy.
You could do
buddy comedy episodes
with Peter and Quagmire
and Joe.
Would you rather get
a massage from a man
or surgery from
a female doctor?
Wow!
And then, beyond that,
Stewie's got this sort of
scientific bent where
it opens the door
to tell all kinds of
sci-fi stories.
Da Vinci must be
my ancestor.
Good Lord!
That's who Bertram's
here to kill.
So, that means
you're Italian.
Of course,
my love for SpaghettiO's
and smoking on the toilet.
It all makes sense.
You know, it really helps
having all those avenues
to pursue.
Creatively, I've always said
come to writing Monty Python,
where any funny idea
that you have
you can somehow fit it
into an episode of Family Guy.
It doesn't even
have to serve the story
as long as it's funny enough.
I got something
for you here.
What is it?
I caught you
a bullfrog outside.
Poked some holes in its back
so it can breathe.
See, look at this...
Oh, boy.
All right, hang on,
hang on.
I also feel like this show
is unique in that...
Because it's animated we can
push boundaries a little bit
further
Some of the things that
our characters say,
if they were coming out
of a live actor or actress,
would seem
sort of off-putting.
Are you telling me
that you have a problem
with me being handicapped?
As a matter of fact, Joe,
yes, I think it's immoral.
It's a lifestyle choice
you're forcing on America.
We handicapped
are a proud people.
Yeah, when you're not
drinking and gambling
on your reservations,
which we gave you.
There are things about
the show that are
maybe gratuitous.
(retching)
But the show doesn't set out
to shock for shock's sake.
It also has to be funny.
(all shouting angrily)
Hey, what are you guys
bellyaching about?
Sir, we are doing all that
we can to stop the killing
of millions of unborn babies.
If you have a few moments,
I'd like you to watch this
video presentation.
Yeah, I got a few minutes.
My wife's getting an abortion.
The "Partial Terms
of Endearment" episode,
the thing to me that's most
significant about the fact
that it couldn't air was
that it was really
the closest we've ever come
to a true modern day
All in the Family episode.
It's a women's
responsibility
to carry it to term.
Well, what if
a woman is raped?
Maybe she should have
thought of that before
she asked me for directions.
Huh?
What about incest,
Peter?
What's incest?
You know how cousin Lou
has that kid whose
eyes touch.
So what, you're saying
Touch Eyes doesn't
deserve to exist?
Well, you don't mind him
when you want a needle threaded.
I'm just saying that
they should have at least
have the option.
How can you say that?
Think of all the love
he's given to Uncle Mom
and Aunt Dad.
Okay, this argument
isn't working.
Peter, what if
carrying the baby to term
would endanger
the mother's life?
I don't know what seven
of those words were.
What if you look
at the ultrasound
and see that the baby
is going to be born
with no arms and no legs?
You name it Mat.
(honks)
Even in our crazy venue,
which is Family Guy,
we felt we'd brought,
you know, a relatively balanced
and sort of
intelligent discussion
of a very, very
difficult subject.
That episode was not
controversial at all.
It's just like "When You Wish
Upon a Weinstein,"
was an episode they felt
that was too controversial.
And it's not at all.
It's, you know...
It's one of the nicer
episodes actually.
Max, Max, Max,
let's not deny
our heritages.
You're Jewish,
you're good with money.
I'm Irish, I drink
and I ban homosexuals
from marching
in my parade.
This is a story
of love and loss,
fathers and sons,
and the foresight to
retain international
merchandising rights.
This is the story
of Star Wars.
We had done a number of
Star Wars gags on the show and,
They were so frequent
that Fox Legal said to us,
"If you're gonna keep
doing these
"we have to get clearance
from Lucasfilm
"because there's just no way
we're not going to get sued."
This will keep you warm
until I get the shelter
built.
You're sure
this is okay?
Yeah, you're just
cutting into the fat.
And we said,
"Ah, well, God,
that's the end of it."
You know, "We're not
going to be able to
do these anymore."
And Lucasfilm surprised us
by saying,
"Yeah, no,
we like this."
What started as a small
idea became a one hour parody
of Star Wars that
Alex Sulkin wrote.
Beep boop beep.
He says there are several
creatures
approaching from the southeast.
That's not
what I said.
I said there ain't
a pack of menthols
on this planet.
I'm a huge Star Wars fan
from way back
as a kid, as many of us are.
Okay, so the door's
going to open
and you guys say, "Freeze,"
and point your guns at 'em.
Or, you know...
Or should it just be me?
Yeah, you know what,
I think that'd be better.
Get out, go, go, go.
Just me.
Oh, I wasn't ready...
Hi!
Those were very fun
for me to work on.
Knowing every line
of those movies
inside and out,
it was fun to kind of
go through it and
make fun of it.
You know, tell the jokes
that you'd always think
of saying.
Where am I?
Jabba's Palace.
Who are you?
Someone who loves you.
Whoa, you are smothering me
and I need my space.
Some of my favorite gags
from the series
come out of some
of those episodes.
I love in the first
Star Wars episode
when they're
in the trash compactor
and Peter finds
an old ratty couch.
PETER: Whoa, whoa, whoa,
stop, stop, stop, stop.
What? What? What?
What?
No, no, no,
twist it.
I am.
No, no, no, no.
No, no, no, other way.
You're twisting it
the wrong way.
Which way?
What do you want
me to do?
Just look down, all right?
Just look at me,
look what I'm doing.
Yeah.
All right, see the way
I'm twisting it?
Yeah.
All right, turn it that way
from your end.
Okay.
Okay, just...
No, no, no, no...
What?
All right, hey,
just put it down.
Put it down,
just drop it.
All right.
We were able to use
all that great
John Williams music.
I mean, they really
gave us the tools to
do this right, and...
And it was because
they trusted us.
They knew that
we were fans and
that we weren't gonna...
We weren't gonna
destroy their property.
(train whistle blowing)
(people talking
indistinctly)
I say, Brian, look,
three rows down.
What?
Is that Tom Bosley?
What would Tom Bosley
be doing on a train
in Switzerland?
I'm almost certain.
Tom!
Did he look?
I don't know.
Well, if I yell,
you have to watch.
Tom Bosley!
No, it's not him.
Huh.
The Road shows have been
a lot of fun.
We started with
"Road to Rhode Island"
in season one.
And, uh, Seth had this idea
to do an episode
based on those Bob Hope,
Bing Crosby road shows.
Seth, as you probably know,
loves Bob Hope.
And, you know,
is very familiar
with those movies
and the music from
those movies and...
So, I think that
having "Road to..."
with Brian and Stewie,
they're sort of our
Bing Crosby and Bob Hope.
Up until that point Stewie had
kind of existed in his own
world.
He would talk to Rupert and
hatch diabolical schemes.
And Brian meanwhile was
kind of Peter's sidekick.
And they were
kind of separate.
And this was the first time
we kind of paired those two,
and it just clicked.
Okay, if everything
worked properly
this should be the exact time
and place that Mort was sent to.
Now, we've just got to
figure out where we are.
Or when we are.
Oh, that's such a douche
time traveler thing to say.
From that point forward
we started
pairing Stewie and Brian
together on stories,
'cause they were
so good together.
And it's a perfect example
of how you can
create a show and then
your writing style...
Other people coming in,
in this case,
the writing staff,
can find things
in your characters that
you didn't see initially.
The Brian-Stewie relationship
which now seems so obvious
was not something
that I thought of when
I was creating the show.
They're always sort of
busting each other's chops
and, uh, antagonistic
towards each other,
but they're also...
I think they've evolved
into their best friends.
(stammering)
Can I just say before...
Can we just like take two...
I love...
You're so brave.
I just love how brave
you're being right now.
This is like the closest
I've ever felt to you.
Okay. Oh, my God,
I was thinking the same thing.
We are so us right now.
Do you know that?
MacFARLANE:
And the Brian-Stewie
episode,
more than anything,
we did to explore
whether or not
two animated characters
with just a single room
can sustain a half hour
purely on the strength
of their characters.
We thought that it might be
interesting to try an episode
where it was almost
like watching a play.
Where it was one location,
two people on stage,
no cutaways,
nothing, just dialogue
for 22 minutes.
It was very polarizing.
People either loved it
or they hated it.
They thought
it was revolutionary,
or they thought
it was just...
You know,
they couldn't get past
the Stewie diaper thing.
(all gasp)
(gasps) Look!
(screams)
He's dead.
Oh, my God.
Nice.
"And Then There Were Fewer"
was our first 16x9 episode,
when we went from
this to this.
And, um, we thought
we'd do this big
splashy visual episode.
I love that episode
because it's the first time
we've really told
a story that complex.
So James Woods murdered
Stephanie and then
he murdered himself.
Criss-cross.
The animators
did an amazing job.
The artists
and the directors
and everybody
that worked on that.
It looks so great
to watch
and the score
is amazing.
It's just a lush score
all the way throughout.
We use anywhere
from a 50 to,
in some cases, a 90-piece
orchestra for every
episode of the show.
Even if people don't know
that what they're hearing
is live music,
is a live orchestra,
on a subconscious level
it classes up the show.
I know that it happens to be
one of Seth's favorite
episodes to this day.
And I think he really
liked approaching it
like a movie.
Mr. Peter.
Mr. Joe.
Mr. Bonnie.
(whispers) She doesn't know
what "mister" means.
Mr. Mort.
Mr. Muriel.
Mayor West Mister.
Oh, my God, seriously.
(singing)
♪ Take me out to pLace
tonight
♪ To a bathroom stall delight
♪ Where a girl
will help you empty
♪ Every last electrolyte ♪
♪ Now everybody
listen if you would
♪ When I tell you
a way of feeling good
♪ Every kitty
needs a ball of string
and every dog a stick
♪ But all you need
is a bag of weed
to really get a kick ♪
♪ Me and Jesus
♪ Come and hug
and squeeze us
♪ 'Cause you know that he's
♪ a simply Christ-errific dude ♪
We do a lot of musical
numbers in Family Guy.
Which is fun for us.
Seth is a big music fan.
And he's very skilled
at executing them.
♪ Now a woman who'll kiss
on a very first date
♪ Is usually a hussy
♪ And a woman who'll kiss
on the second time out
♪ Is anything but fussy
♪ But a woman who'll wait
'till the third time around
♪ Head in the clouds,
feet on the ground
♪ She's the girl
he's glad he's found
♪ She's his Shipoopi ♪
MacFARLANE: Shipoopi
was so elaborately
choreographed
and then the visuals,
which Dan Povenmire,
the director,
spent a ton of time working on,
really hit every point
in the orchestration.
And the thing
that I've always loved
about the show is...
When I talk to my son
and his friends, you know,
they don't know
what Shipoopi is.
They might not know,
you know, who Gene Kelly was,
but they're loving
the musical, segments.
And it's like,
how did Seth make
10 million teenage boys
fans of musicals?
♪ It's a wonderful day for pie
♪ You can ask
all the birds in the sky
♪ And they'll
tell you real sweet,
with a musical tweet
♪ It's a wonderful day
for pie ♪
Our season seven premiere
was an episode called
"Road to the Multiverse."
And there's this great
musical number called
It's A Wonderful Day
for Pie,
which is, you know,
as devoid of content
as it sounds.
It's just about Peter
and Lois singing about
how much they love pie.
But the animation
in that sequence
is amazing.
Visually, it was just fantastic
to see our characters
animated in a Disney style.
I just thought
that was so well done.
And it was
a lot of fun.
And we
sort of improvised
some of the lyrics
in the room.
Seth just came out with...
(as Peter)
♪ It's a wonderful
day for pie
And one of us goes...
(as Cleveland)
♪ And it smells
so much better than I ♪
It was Cleveland as a skunk
and it just came together.
And, uh,
that was a great piece.
One of my favorites.
♪ I know you just
can't wait to stare
♪ At all that
luscious orange hair
♪ But, boy, before you
touch a single curl
♪ You must impress
that ultra-bloomin'
♪ All-consumin',
poorly groomin'
♪ Down's Syndrome girl ♪
The Down's Syndrome Girl song
was fun for me because
it was the first time
I had written lyrics
and a tune.
Which I basically went in
and sang for Walter Murphy
who then arranged it and
actually made it sound good.
It's a lot of fun
for us to...
You know,
to write a song lyric
and have a great composer
like Walter Murphy or Ron Jones
set it to music.
♪ Each bell would peal
with a silvery zeal
♪ As the holiday feeling
was filling us
♪ But now instead,
all we're feeling is dread
♪ Because Christmastime
is killing us ♪
When we did our
Christmas episode,
I had originally envisioned
something like Rudolph
that had, like,
four or five, six
musical numbers in it.
We ended up, like,
doing two or three.
And I had written
this lyric about how...
I was making a comment
on how crazy Christmas
has become
and what it takes
out of us all.
And when the smoke cleared,
it was a success.
And we were nominated
for an Emmy.
But also, a great
unexpected thrill was
we were nominated
for a Grammy.
♪ You have AIDS
♪ Yes, you have AIDS
♪ Not HIV but full blown AIDS ♪
MacFARLANE:
I think the first song that
the barbershop quartet did
was the AIDS song.
And that's
a perfect example
of another reason
for using that orchestra
and trying to be
so musically legit.
Because it allows you
to get away with content
that you wouldn't otherwise
be able to get away with.
Yeah, talk about
making a subject matter
a little more palatable.
People love the absurdity
of these guys singing such
an outrageous lyric,
but what Seth
appreciates about it is
how unbelievably talented
these guys are and were
in these pieces, musically.
It provides
a musical cushion
that prevents you from
being completely crass,
if you're being that crass
in the first place.
♪ You'll never have
to wear a condom
♪ When you do it
with your wife
♪ Or anyone else
you do it with
♪ We promise not to tell ♪
I also like the little things
that we do here and there,
like, Stewie singing
little folk songs,
Stewie making up his own,
you know, little songs,
talking about, "Playing the
G-chord
"and here we go
to the D-chord."
♪ Then Brian comes in
and I change up the tempo
♪ Brian comes in
and it changes the song
♪ Looking at me like
he thinks I'm a douche bag
♪ But he's gonna learn
pretty fast that he's wrong
♪ Hey, Brian, why are you
bringing me down, man?
♪ Why are you
bringing me down?
♪ Don't bring me down! ♪
Music and lyrics
by Stewie Griffin.
MacFARLANE:
It's amazing to me
that the show has had
the cultural impact
that it has.
For a long while,
The Simpsons was
really the only show
that had broken out
in this way
and I always hoped
we would have a prayer of
maybe doing that as well.
And I think
we've done that.
Ah!
SMITH: One of the great things
now is that we're syndicated.
So, we're on all the time.
And old people
like us now.
I have an Auntie Philly
who's 92.
She loves Family Guy
and she won't let
any of her friends
in the room when it's on
because old people
talk back to the television.
She wants to hear it.
OLD WOMAN: What?
OLD MAN: Huh?
What?
Huh?
I forget.
I said it before,
but we're so thankful
to our fans
for bringing the show
back from the dead,
that I almost feel like
we owe it to them
to give 110% every day
to every episode.
I try to interact with
the fans as much as I can.
I don't know if you
can see right now,
but I'm actually
eight months pregnant.
And this is a fan's baby.
You get crazy when
you're pregnant.
(laughing)
(sobbing)
I feel like if you love me
from afar then the least I
can do is love you back.
And if that means carrying
your child, so be it.
I love my fans.
Keep digging, you know?
It feels like there's
no more stories to tell
and then we dig for a while
and something pops up that,
"Oh, we haven't done that."
(roaring)
What's next is, I guess,
episode 300.
And I'll have
even more gray hair
and bigger circles
under my eyes.
I'm here for
the early bird special.
MacFARLANE:
A Family Guy movie
would be a logical extension.
But, with an animated show,
you can do pretty much
anything.
There's nothing
you can't do.
So what is the reason
to make a movie?
Without giving
anything away,
I think we've hit on
the answer to that.
So when that
Family Guy movie
does come around,
suffice it to say,
it will be something that
is not do-able on TV.
(farts)
Sorry.
It's been building up
for a while.
I don't have a favorite
character at this point.
I'm recording voices so much.
Hi, pardner.
I'm a cattle rustler.
I rustle cattle.
Oh, that's turning out good.
I'm partial to Brian.
Brian.
Brian Steele.
Ooh, good heavens!
He's the only character that I
don't leave the booth with a
you know sore throat.
Seems to me you should spend
less time working for the
paper
and more time working on that
novel you've been working on...
you know...
Ah!